准备好了吗  孩子们
Are you ready, kids?
好了船长
Aye aye, captain
我听不见
I can't hear you
好了船长
Aye aye, captain
是谁住在深海的大菠萝里
Who lives in a pineapple under the sea?
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
方方黄黄伸缩自如
Absorbent and yellow and porous is he
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
如果四处探险是你的愿望
If nautical nonsense be something you wish
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
那就敲敲甲板让大鱼开路
Then drop on the deck and flop like a fish
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
准备
Ready
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
妙手回春
编剧
翻译: 1440kHz
分镜总监
指导总监
动画总监
统筹
监制
本字幕仅限学习交流
严禁用于商业用途
春天里喝甜茶最舒服了
Nothin' better than sweet tea in springtime
海绵宝宝来了
There's SpongeBob now
我的树
My tree
嗨  珊迪
Hi, Sandy
我直接进来了
I let myself in
希望你不介意
Hope you don't mind
干嘛一副苦瓜脸
Why the long face?
你的树
Your tree
怎么一回事
What happened?
我不知道
I have no idea
这棵老橡树现在应该是花开正旺才对
This old oak should be in full bloom right now
不应该跟垂柳一样垂泪
not weepin' like a willow
你没有原子橡果射线枪什么的吗
Well, don't you have some kind of
atomic acorn ray or something?
根本没那玩意
That ain't a thing
来  帮我操作我的核动力
Here, help me with my nuclear-powered
全自动树皮电击枪
bark-o-matic zapatron
起效了
It's working
搞得反而更严重了
That just made it worse
我该怎么办才好
What am I gonna do?
我认识一个园艺大师
I know someone who's great at gardening
维生素
Vitamins?
恶心死了
That's disgusting
章鱼哥  你又成功了
Squidward, you've done it again
又是一朵奇葩
Another fleur de force
章鱼哥
Squidward
章鱼哥  我需要你来帮忙
Squidward, I need your help
我的树出毛病了
Something is wrong with my tree
看得出来你们一点都不尊重
I can see you don't have any respect
我们优雅的花儿朋友
for our fine floral friends
别把我扯进去
Count me out
我只打理自己的花园
I'll tend my own garden
章鱼哥  求你了
Squidward, please?
听说你可是全裤头村最厉害的园艺家
I heard you're the greatest gardener in Bikini Bottom
而且所有植物都喜欢你
And that all plants love you
好吧  去就去
Alright, I'll do it
但是有一个条件
On one condition, that is
不准质疑
No one questions
或者打断我的流程
or interrupts my process
好吧
Okay
所以我们对树做了测量评估
So we tested my tree to gauge its--
不必多说
Say no more
我自己就能诊断
I can diagnose it myself
有点橡树味  怪怪的坚果味
Notes of oak, a bit nutty
还有一丝丝悲苦味
and a hint of distress
没有脉搏
No pulse
跟我担心的一样
It's just as I feared
这棵树得了树皮树枝病
This tree has bark and branch disease
没听说过那种病
I ain't never heard of that
很严重吗
Is it serious?
别担心  珊迪小姐
Don't worry, Miss Sandy
章鱼哥是咱这最厉害的师傅
Squidward's the best we've got
肥料
Fertilizer
新鲜有机肥
Fresh manure
隔着头盔咋闻到味的
How did he smell through the helmet?
矿泉水
Mineral water
剪子
Shears
简简单单
Easy-peasy
好家伙
Well, I'll be
真见鬼
Barnacles
比我预想的还要严重
This is more serious than I thought
怎么
What the?
章鱼哥  拿这么多风铃跟护符来干嘛
Squidward, what in tarnation
are all these chimes and charms for?
我们要来试试替代园艺法
We are going to try a little alternative gardening
[ 替代园艺法：改自替代疗法
指在西医之外、缺乏科学根据的疗法 ]
这都是流程的一部分
It's all part of the process
要引导这棵树正念冥想
We're going to guide the tree in mindful meditation
需要想象它成长的样子
We need to visualize its growth
章鱼哥金曲
深呼吸
Take a deep breath
感受树根
Feel the roots of the tree
跟着我念
Repeat after me
我的树皮很强壮  我的树枝很粗壮
My bark is strong, my branches thick
我的花蕾很茂盛
My buds are bountiful
我的耳朵很难受
My ears are bleeding
我的屁股很漂亮
My butt is beautiful
一点小插曲而已
A minor hiccup
相信我的流程
Trust the process
好了  章鱼哥
Alright, Squidward
你这流程  到底还要做多久
Just how much longer is this "process" going to take?
珊迪  这可得看树的情况
Well, Sandy, that's up to the tree
流程没完  我就不走
But I'll stay here as long as it takes
可能要好几天
It could be days
甚至好几周
Even weeks
好几周吗
Weeks, huh?
真够久的
Ain't that somethin'?
这棵树得补充树液
This tree needs sap
要赶快
ASAP
都是流程的一部分
Part of the process
章鱼哥
Squidward
都是为了树好
It's for the tree
都是流程的一部分
Part of the process
流程
The process
经过很多部分流程后
不会吧
Oh no
他又在大半夜来搞园艺了
He's night gardening again
流程
The process
够了
Enough
给我得了
That's it
我受够这个破流程了
I've had it with his consarned "process"
章鱼哥
Squidward
我
I
给我得了
That's it
我受够你动不动就来打扰了
I've had it with your constant interruptions
别来烦我搞好流程
You need to leave me to my process
我会向他们证明的
I'll show them
证明给他们所有人看
I'll show them all
章鱼哥失败得也够久了
Squidward's failed for long enough
但愿你能帮我劝他离开  海绵宝宝
Hopefully, you can help me
convince him to leave, SpongeBob
我的树
My tree
真不敢相信
I can't believe it
章鱼哥做到了不可能的事
Squidward really did the impossible
对
Yeah
不可能
Impossible
看
Look
什么鬼
What in tarnation?
这都是
A-are these
章鱼哥的画吗
Squidward's paintings?
以前是  珊迪
They were, Sandy
但现在都被我剪下来了
but I cut them up
我不只把树给治好了
I didn't just fix the tree
还让它更加美妙
I turned it into something better
更加壮观了
Something sublime
现在我不仅是裤头村最厉害的园艺家
Now I'm not only the greatest gardener in Bikini Bottom
还是全世界最厉害的艺术家
I'm the greatest artist in the world
这下可好
Great
我的树还病着
My tree is still sick
章鱼哥现在又在发癫傻乐
and now Squidward's actin' like a dang ninny
可惜没法直接问问树出了什么毛病
Too bad we can't just ask the tree what's wrong with it
直接问树
Ask the tree?
真是个好办法
That's a great idea
而且我正好有道具
And I think I have just the doodad
我的跨物种翻译机
My inter-species translator
从来没在植物身上用过
I've never tried it on plant life
喂  喂
Testing, testing
听得到吗
Can ya hear me?
可以  珊迪
Yes, Sandy
能听得到
I can hear you
好家伙
Woo doggy
成功了
It worked
我感觉到有个黏滑的东西在我身上爬
And I can feel something
rather slimy crawling around me
那个嘛
Yeah
不用理他
Don't mind him none
不过既然我们能聊天了
But now that we can chat
问下是什么害你病得树枝一直掉呢
what seems to be bringin' your branches down?
我并没有病  珊迪
I'm not suffering from an illness, Sandy
没病吗
You ain't?
那你怎么了呢
Then what's wrong?
有个很重的东西
Something quite heavy
连续几天都压住了我的根
has been crushing my roots for days now
一定是星期天兜完风把车忘在那了
Must'a left her there after my Sunday drive
这样舒服多了
That is much better
终于可以摆脱这些垃圾了
I can finally be rid of all this rubbish
可惜了你的画  章鱼哥
Sorry about your paintings, Squidward
我白白毁掉了我的画
I destroyed my paintings for nothing
才没有  章鱼哥
No, Squidward
虽然你毁了画
You destroyed your paintings
却换来了友情
for friendship
那还是白白毁掉比较好
I'd rather have the nothing
不必担心  亲爱的章鱼哥
Fret not, dear Squidward
正因为你有这份关怀的心
The way you care
才能成为裤头村最厉害的园艺家
makes you the greatest gardener in Bikini Bottom
那真是
Why, that's
真是我听过最贴心的一句好话了
That's the nicest thing anyone has ever said to me
我想送你一份薄礼  以示感谢
I'd like to give you a small token of my gratitude
谢谢
Thank you
蟹老板
生日快乐
编剧
分镜总监
翻译: 1440kHz
指导总监
动画总监
统筹
监制
本字幕仅限学习交流
严禁用于商业用途
蟹堡王
章鱼哥
Hey, Squidward
知道明天是什么日子吗
Do you know what day tomorrow is?
距离死亡又接近了一天
Another day closer to death?
笨蛋
Silly
要不要我给你个提示
How 'bout I give you a hint?
是蟹老板的生日
It's Mr. Krabs' birthday
要送他什么
What should we get him?
什么
What?
想都别想
Oh, no, you don't
你们两个不准  我再重复一遍
You two are not, I repeat
不准给我买生日礼物
not to be getting me a birthday present
你们送我的每个礼物
Every single one you've gotten me
都是彻头彻尾的灾难
has been a total disaster
那些都是海绵宝宝一个人送的
Those were all from SpongeBob
我不管
I don't care
以及不准送礼
And no presents
所以要给他送什么呢
So, what should we get him?
什么
What?
他都说了
You heard him
不准送礼物
No presents
他那是口是心非
He doesn't mean it
他真的很想要礼物
He really wants one
他那是在利用逆反心理
He's using reverse psychology
而你这脑子都长反了
And you're using reverse brains
别把我扯进来
Count me out
上流百货会营业到很晚
Upturn's Department Store is open late
我要给他找个好礼物
I'll get him something nice
就说是我们两个一起送的
And I'll say it's from the both of us
我准备好了
I'm ready
蟹老板生日
Krabby birthday
我准备好了
I'm ready
蟹老板生日
Krabby birthday
等一下
Wait a minute
这是我们两个一起送的
It's from the both of us
我们两个一起
The both of us?
最好跟过去
You'd better go
省得他又买到什么笨玩意
and make sure he doesn't get something stupid again
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob
等等我
Wait for me
果不其然
Typical
上流百货
应该要给他买巧克力直升飞机
Should we get him a chocolate helicopter?
还是喷气背包呢
Or a jet pack?
跳跳糖豆
Jumping jellybeans?
不该
No
还是
And
不该
no
等一下
Hold it
快看
Look
危险宠物区
The Dangerous Pets Department
危险宠物
大家都爱需要承担责任的礼物
Everyone loves the gift of responsibility
等等
Wait
海绵宝宝  不要
SpongeBob, no
那玩意很危险的
That thing's dangerous
这个小可爱才不危险呢
Not this widdle cutie-pie
它喜欢你
He likes you
这个倒可能会危险
Now this one can be dangerous
派大星
Patrick?
派大星哪里危险了
What's so dangerous about Patrick?
现在想起来了
Now I remember
情怀区
The Sentimental Department?
对  章鱼哥
Yes, Squidward
这里卖的都是能动情的东西
This is where they sell emotional objects
像是这些照片  拍的都是慈祥老母亲
Like these photos of kindly old mothers
她让我想起了
She reminds me of
我妈
my mom
情书
情书还有促销哦
There's a sale on love letters
致我亲爱的翻车鱼
"My darling Sunfish
我多么渴望凝视你鳃上的细丝
how I long to gaze upon the filaments of your gills
你的小孔雀鱼献上
From your little guppy"?
写得
That's so
好优美
beautiful
就给蟹老板送那个吧
Let's get that for Mr. Krabs
不行  必须得触动他的情怀
No It has to be something sentimental
还要对他有特殊意义
and personal to him
特殊意义
Personal?
说什么
What's that?
泰迪熊说  蟹老板家里可以找到线索
Teddy Bear says you'll find a clue in Mr. Krabs' house
泰迪熊吗
Teddy Bear?
对  我就是那么说的
Yup, that's what I said
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob
等等
Wait
太疯狂了
This is crazy
万一吵醒他
What if he wakes up
让他发现我们在他家咋办
and finds us in his house?
不会的
He won't
他跟珍珍晚上向来睡得很死
He and Pearl are heavy sleepers
声音再大都吵不醒他们
Loud noises never wake them up
那么
Well
那样的话
in that case
好办法
Great idea
你从那边进去
You go in that way
我就爬这扇刚好没关的窗户进去
and I'll climb in
through this conveniently open window
果不其然
Typical
找到什么了没
You find anything?
没
No
那你呢
What about you?
还没
Nothing yet
我也没
Me neither
你说啥
What'd you say?
我说  我也没
I said, "Me neither"
快看这张照片
Look at this photo
是蟹老板开蟹堡王之前的旧餐车
It's Krabs' old food cart before he had The Krusty Krab
他以前经常把它停在酷乐湖海滩上
He used to park it on the beach at Goo Lagoon
送他这个当情怀礼物刚刚好
It would make the perfect
sentimental birthday gift for him
没错
It sure would
我知道那个禁止游泳标志在哪
I know right where that no swimming sign is
来吧  我们走
Come on, let's go
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob
等等
Wait
谁
Who?
什么
What?
在哪
Where?
乱七八糟的
What a mess
一定是我的不安蟹爪综合征又发作了
Musta been me restless claw syndrome again
欢迎来到酷乐湖
没理由相信他的旧餐车会在
There's no reason to believe that his old cart would be
这里吗
here?
干得漂亮  章鱼哥
Great work, Squidward
你找到它了
You found it
真是好家伙
Well, I'll be dipped in batter
快点
Come on
咱们来把它摆正  推去蟹堡王
Let's get it upright and wheel it to the Krusty Krab
它闹鬼了
It's haunted
小偷
Burglars
抢匪
Robbers
恶贼
Thieves
想偷我老斯纳格的家  是吗
Trying to steal Old Snug's home, are ya?
寄居蟹可是也有住宅权的
Well, hermit crabs have housing rights too, you know?
抱歉  这位
Sorry, Mister, uh
斯纳格先生
Snug?
我们以为这辆车没人要
We thought this cart was abandoned
是这样的  它以前是我们老板的
You see, it used to belong to our boss
我们觉得可以给他个惊喜
And we thought we'd surprise him
送他这个当生日礼物
by giving it to him on his birthday
这可是个情怀礼物啊
You know, a sentimental gift
情怀是吗
Sentimental, eh?
那个嘛
Well
我可拒绝不了情怀
I'm a sucker for sentiment
这么说吧
Tell you what
再给我找样东西当家
find me another thing I could use as a home
我就把这辆旧车给你们
and I'll give you this old cart
垃圾桶
Trashcan?
不行
Nope
公共厕所
Porta Potty?
不行
Nope
冰箱
Refrigerator?
不行
Nope
知道我一直想要什么吗
You know what I always wanted?
我要拿船来当家
A boat for a house
不用太高档
Not anything fancy
一艘简陋的小船就行了
A small, humble boat would do
你们照办  就能成交
You do that and you've got a deal
第二天
整晚没睡  净打扫我卧室了
Up all night cleaning me room
这破生日提醒我已经上年纪了
Lousy birthday reminding me I'm an old krab
惊喜
Surprise
有埋伏
Ambush
有偷袭
Sneak attack
打了就跑
Hit and run
是你们两个啊
It's you two
生日快乐  蟹老板
Happy Birthday, Mr. Krabs
是我以前的蟹堡餐车
Me old Krabby Kart?
都是我想的主意
It was all my idea
我很久以前就把这辆车落在了酷乐湖
I left this cart at Goo Lagoon a long time ago
因为我讨厌它
because I hated it
都是海绵宝宝想的主意
It was all SpongeBob's idea
这个垃圾让我想起了从前的日子
This piece of junk reminds me of the old days
那时候我完全没有钱
when I had no money
没有钱吗
No money?
难怪你会讨厌它
No wonder you hate it
怎么
What the--
我的收银船哪去了
Where's me register boat?
我们拿它来换你的旧车了
We traded it for your old cart
惊喜
Surprise?
明白了
I see
那个装着我钱的收银机呢
And where's the cash register filled with me money?
有可能还在船上吧
It's probably still in the boat?
你们两个把我船和收银机搞回来
You two get me boat and register back
我所有钱也要搞回来
with all me money
不然我就把你们大卸八块
or I'll rip youse limb from limb
再组装成现代艺术
and reassemble youse into modern art
好酷
Cool
快去
Go
马上
now
斯纳格先生
Mr. Snug?
我们得把船要回来
We need this boat back
他不在这
He's not here
但是收银机还在
But the cash register is
钱都没有了
The money's gone
快看
Look
别走
Hold it
好了  斯纳格
Alright, Snug
钱都哪去了
Where's the money?
都在我背上呢
It's on my back
我把钱全花来买这个明朝花瓶
I used it all to buy this Imperial Ming vase
当作我的新家了
as my new home
再见
Toodles
你怎么看待现代艺术
How do you feel about modern art?
我觉得它摈弃了历史风格
I find its rejection of historical styles
让我耳目一新
to be quite refreshing
祝我生日快乐
Happy birthday to me
对不起
We're sorry
收银机里面的钱要不回来了
We couldn't get your money back from the register
干嘛这么高兴  蟹老板
Why so happy, Mr. Krabs?
还有
And
餐车去哪了
where's the cart?
有个客人把它当作收藏品了
A customer recognized it as a collector's item
给的钱远远超过了它的实际价值
He paid me way more than it was worth
今天简直是最棒的生日
Best birthday ever
当然这都是我想的主意
Of course, it was all my idea
当然我也得扣你未来的工资
And of course, I'll have to dock your future pay
垫我收银机里的钱  章鱼哥先生
for the contents of me register, Mr. Squidward
可是
But--
来吧  小子
Come on, boy-o
我们今天来休假
We're taking a day off
要不要去博物馆
How about a museum?
我觉得现代艺术摈弃了历史风格
I find modern art's rejection of historical styles
让我耳目一新  你说是不是
quite refreshing, don't you?
我完全同意
I completely agree
又是
Once again
果不其然
typical